Rajeev Jain

PRINCIPAL RESEARCH SOFTWARE SPECIALIST · ARGONNE NATIONAL LABORATORY CHICAGO · MATHEMATICS AND COMPUTER SCIENCE ♠ rajeeja.github.io ☑ rajeeja@gmail.com ☐ +1 312-725-3380 in linkedin ☎ google scholar

Summary

I have 14 years of experience managing/developing software projects and two masters degree: one in computer science and the other in structural enginneering. I like to manage risks, solve-problems and learn new things, I am familiar with several programming languages and tools used to execute complex projects.

Work Experience

Principal Research Software Specialist, Mathematics and Computer Science Argonne National Laboratory 2018 - 2022

- ⇒ Conceptualized software products, developed coding/testing practices and supervised junior developers to accomplish project goals.
- ⇒ Significantly reduced the time taken by domain scientists to launch and analyze large runs on super-computers.
- ⇒ Used our hyperparameter optimization on COVID-19 deep neural network (DNN) models and delivered improved results. Scripted big runs on HPC clusters.
- Wrote reports and published papers in peer-reviewed journals and conferences such as the supercomputing conference.

Software Developement Specialist, Mathematics and Computer Science Argonne National Laboratory 2011 - 2018

- ⇒ Handled the coupled urban exascale simulation project, lead a diverse team of experts from different national labs and universities.
- ⇒ My reactor generator tool was used by Kitware Inc. to write and get SBIR funding Phase 1 for \$225k and Phase 2 for \$750k for a 2 year period. They developed GUI and added some new features to the toolset.
- ⇒ Greatly improved the runtime and memory utilization of simulation codes by using distributed computing techniques and libraries.
- ⇒ Lead the developer of MeshKit, presented yearly updates to the U.S. scientific funding agencies located in Washington D.C.

2009 - 2011 Pre-doctoral Appointee, Mathematics and Computer Science

Argonne National Laboratory

⇒ Gathered requirements and developed the scalable reactor geometry and mesh generation (RGG) tool using C++ and other open-source libraries.

Research and Teaching Assistant, Civil Engineering in the School of Sustainable Engineering and the Built Environment Arizona State University

- ⇒ Mentored students to solve structural engineering problems and graded assignements.
- ⇒ Wrote an MPI based optimization algorithm for finding the best dimensions in a FEM-based blast simulation problem using LS-DYNA software.

2006 - 2007 Project Engineer, SAP/Java

WIPRO TECHNOLOGIES, BANGALORE/HYDERABAD, INDIA

- ⇒ Completed Java programming course and worked on a mobile payment systems for Nokia (Bangalore).
- ⇒ 3 months of training in SAP ABAP and started working on a process-optimization project with Kodak (Hyderabad).

Research Trainee, Engineering Research Division Summer 2005

TATA MOTORS, PUNE, INDIA

⇒ Performed hot and cold circuit trials on an automobile engine fitted with a 3rd party retarder.

SOFTWARE PROJECTS

2020 – present

GITHUB LINK

Helped design and code the first draft of the popular UXARRAY API, wrote python functions to integrate and read/write unstructured grids.

Co-Developer, ECP-CANDLE 2016 – present

GITHUB LINK

Published papers on model robustness with counterfactuals / noise injection and hyper-parameter optimization framework "Supervisor". Currently focussed on testing claims made by the recent artificial inteligence (AI-based) cancer drug-response papers, creating a framework for understanding model sensitivity and XAI.

2007 - 2009

2018 – present Co-Developer, Flash-X

DOCUMENTATION

Designed/coded asynchronous write and compression of HDF5 checkpoint file. Help with performance benchmarking on DOE supercomputers, CI, documentation. Review/manage GitHub policies, actions, PRs, issues etc.

2009 - 2016

Lead Developer, MeshKit

BITBUCKET LINK

Principal Investigator for MeshKit (mesh generation C++ toolkit) for the reactor geometry generation package (RGG). Wrote several mesh/geometry generation algorithms and published in peer-reviewed conferences/journals.

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- R. Jain, A. Shah. J. Mohd-Yusof. et al. "Probing Decision Boundaries in Cancer Data Using Noise Injection and Counterfactual Analysis." (2021)
- 2. **R. Jain**, K. Weide. S. Chawdhary. T. Klostermann. "Checkpoint/Restart for Lagrangian particle mesh with AMR in community code FLASH-X." *arXiv preprint arXiv:2103.04267* (2021)
- 3. **R. Jain**, X. Luo. G. Sever. T. Hong. C. Catlett. "Representation and evolution of urban weather boundary conditions in downtown Chicago." *Journal of Building Performance Simulation* 13, 182–194 (2020)
- 4. J. M. Wozniak. **R. Jain**, P. Balaprakash. et al. "Candle/supervisor: A workflow framework for machine learning applied to cancer research." *BMC bioinformatics* 19, 59–69 (2018)
- 5. P. O'Leary. J. Becker. R. O'Bara. D. Thompson. **R. Jain**, et al. "Providing a Graphical Tool for Modeling Reactor Cores." *Transactions of the American Nuclear Society* 118, (2018)
- 6. **R. Jain**, T. J. Tautges. "PostBL: Post-mesh boundary layer mesh generation tool." *Proceedings of the 22nd International Meshing Roundtable* 331–348 (2014)
- 7. T. J. Tautges. **R. Jain**, "Creating geometry and mesh models for nuclear reactor core geometries using a lattice hierarchy-based approach." *Engineering with Computers* 28, 319–329 (2012)
- 8. R. Jain, "M.S. Thesis: Blast Mitigation solutions via FEM-Based Design Optimization." (2009)

Honors

2020	Invited: Reviewer and Program Committee Memb	ber, Managed and reviewed papers	NUMGRID
2010 – present	Mentor, Supervised several summer students/posto	docs and staff members — Argonne National L	ABORATORY
2015	Reviewer and Session Chair Computational Geometries, SNA and MC conference		CONFERENCE
2015-2017	Advisor and Developer Commercialization of RGC	G: click for details KITWARE INC. FOR SBIR PH	ase I and II
2011	Co-chair Argo	nne/CSUI Undergraduate/Graduate Research	Symposium
2007 - 2009	University Graduate Fellowship, \$4000	Arizona State	University
2004 - 2004	ıst Prize for Low Budget Car Design Contest, INR	R 40k+ TECH FEST IIT KHARAGPUR AND MINDA	Ltd. Delhi

EDUCATION

2017 – 2020	Masters of Science Computer Science	University of Chicago
2007 – 2009	Master of Science Structural Engg. (Minor Computer Science)	Arizona State University
2002 – 2006	B.Tech Mechanical Engineering	IIT Dhanbad, India

OTHER SKILLS AND ACTIVITIES

2012-present	Mentor School kids with STEM Mentoring Cafe	
2011-2017	Reviewer International Meshing Roundtable (IMR).	
2015	Reviewer SBIR (Small Business Funding Proposals)	
2015	ATPESC scholar world-class training for selected applicants on HPC and big data	
2017-present	Member Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) and American Nuclear Society (ANS).	
	Following: Cricket, Biking, Table-tennis, Crypto-currencies and International affairs.	